<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "./dtd/document-v11.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Jakarta POI - Case Studies</title>
    <authors>
      <person id="AO" name="Andrew C. Oliver" email="acoliver@apache.org"/>
      <person id="CR" name="Cameron Riley" email="crileyNO@SPAMekmail.com"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  
  <body>
    <section title="Introduction">
       <p>
          A number of people are using POI for a variety of purposes.  As with
          any new API or technology, the first question people generally ask
          is not "how can I" but rather "Who else is doing what I'm about to 
          do?"  This is understandable with the abismal success rate in the 
          software business.  These case statements are meant to help create
          confidence and understanding.
       </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Submitting a Case Study">
       <p>
          We are actively seeking case studies for this page (after all it 
          just started).  Andy Oliver (acoliver at apache dot org) has 
          agreed to have a few T-Shirts printed with the POI logo (once its
          chosen) for the first
          few best submissions.  To submit a case study, either  
          <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/poi/getinvolved/index.html">
          submit a patch for this page</link> (preferred) or email it to the 
          <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">mailing list
          </link>.  
       </p>
    </section>
    <section title="Case Studies">
      <section title="Bank of Lithuania">
        <p>
          The <link href="http://www.lbank.lt">Bank of Lithuania</link>
          reports financial statistical data to Excel format using the 
          <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/poi">Jakarta POI</link>
          project's <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/poi/hssf">
          HSSF</link> API.  The system is based on Oracle JServer and
          utilizes a Java stored procedure that outputs to XLS format
          using the HSSF API.  - Arian Lashkov (alaskov at lbank.lt)
        </p>
      </section>
      <section title="Bit Tracker by Tracker Inc., and ThinkVirtual">
        <p>
Bit Tracker (http://www.bittracker.com) is the world's first and only web-based drill bit tracking system to manage your company's critical bit information and use that data to its full potential. It manages all bit related data, including their usage, locations, how they were used, and results such as rate of penetration and dull grade after use.  This data needs to be available in Excel format for backwards compatibility and other uses in the industry.  After using CSV and HTML formats, we needed something better for creating the spreadsheets and POI is the answer.  It works great and was easy to implement.  Kudos to the POI team.
        </p>
        <p>
           Travis Reeder (travis at thinkvirtual dot com)
        </p>
      </section>
      <section title="Edwards And Kelcey Technology">
      <p>
      Edwards and Kelcey Technology (http://www.ekcorp.com/) developed a 
      Facility
      Managament and Maintenance System for the Telecommunications industry 
      based
      on Turbine and Velocity. Originally the invoicing was done with a simple 
      CVS
      sheet which was then marked up by accounts and customized for each client.
      As growth has been consistent with the application, the requirement for
      invoices that need not be touched by hand increased. POI provided the
      solution to this issue, integrating easily and transparently into the
      system. POI HSSF was used to create the invoices directly from the server
      in
      Excel 97 format and now services over 150 unique invoices per month.
      </p>
      <p>
      Cameron Riley (crileyNO@ SPAMekmail.com)
      </p>
     </section>
    </section>
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Apache Software Foundation All rights reserved.
      $Revision$ $Date$
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
