<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
   ====================================================================
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
   ====================================================================
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "../dtd/document-v11.dtd">

<document>
    <header>
        <title>POI-HPBF - A Guide to the Publisher File Format</title>
        <subtitle>Overview</subtitle>
        <authors>
            <person name="Nick Burch" email="nick at torchbox dot com"/>
        </authors>
    </header>

    <body>
        <section><title>Document Streams</title>
		<p>
		The file is made up of a number of POIFS streams. A typical
        file will be made up as follows:
		</p>
<source>
Root Entry -
  Objects -
    (no children)
  SummaryInformation <(0x05)SummaryInformation>
  DocumentSummaryInformation <(0x05)DocumentSummaryInformation>
  Escher -
    EscherStm
    EscherDelayStm
  Quill -
    QuillSub -
      CONTENTS
      CompObj <(0x01)CompObj>
  Envelope
  Contents
  Internal <(0x03)Internal>
  CompObj <(0x01)CompObj>
  VBA -
    (no children)
</source>
		</section>
        <section><title>Changing Text</title>
		<p>If you make a change to the text of a file, but not change
          how much text there is, then the <em>CONTENTS</em> stream
          will undergo a small change, and the <em>Contents</em> stream
          will undergo a large change.</p>
        <p>If you make a change to the text of a file, and change the
          amount of text there is, then both the <em>Contents</em> and
          the <em>CONTENTS</em> streams change.</p>
		</section>
        <section><title>Changing Shapes</title>
        <p>If you alter the size of a textbox, but make no text changes,
          then both <em>Contents</em> and <em>CONTENTS</em> streams
          change. There are no changes to the Escher streams.</p>
        <p>If you set the background colour of a textbox, but make
          no changes to the text,
		</section>
        <section><title>Structure of CONTENTS</title>
        <p>First we have "CHNKINK ", followed by 24 bytes.</p>
        <p>Next we have 20 sequences of 24 bytes each. If the first two bytes
         at 0x1800, then that sequence entry exists, but if it's 0x0000 then
         the entry doesn't exist. If it does exist, we then have 4 bytes of
         upper case ASCII text, followed by three little endian shorts.
         The first of these seems to be the count of that type, the second is
         usually 1, the third is usually zero. The we have another 4 bytes of
         upper case ASCII text, normally but not always the same as the first
         text. Finally, we have an unsigned little endian 32 bit offset to
         the start of the data for this, then an unsigned little endian
         32 bit offset of the length of this section.</p>
        <p>Normally, the first sequence entry is for TEXT, and the text data
         will start at 0x200. After that is normally two or three STSH entries
         (so the first short has values 0, then 1, then 2). After that it
         seems to vary.</p>
        <p>At 0x200 we have the text, stored as little endian 16 bit unicode.</p>
        <p>After the text comes all sorts of other stuff, presumably as 
         described by the sequences.</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
